Though SQL is a keyword-based language, it
is a programming language.
With any programming language, what we want
to happen and what happens often differ.
In this domain on troubleshooting, we will
see how to troubleshoot both syntax and runtime
errors.
As we do this, take note of the most common
mistakes people make when building queries.
This way, if this happens to you, you will
know what to do.
This domain is all about going through two
types of errors: syntax errors and runtime
errors.
For the most part, a syntax error will cause
a statement not to run, and a runtime error
will appear when there are no syntax errors
present, but something in a query is causing
it not to run properly.
Some errors occur when trying to work with
database objects.
Take a look at this statement attempting to
add a column to an existing table in the BikeRepair
database.
I will execute this statement, and immediately
we see an error about an object type.
This error is a syntax error because whoever
built this query did not specify the type
of object being altered.
I will change this to an ALTER TABLE statement.
I will attempt to execute this again.
Now, it is saying there is incorrect syntax
near the keyword column.
When adding something to a table, SQL knows
we are adding a column, so the keyword is
unnecessary.
Let's try this again.
Now, when we execute it, this works.
Let me show you a runtime error as it pertains
to working with objects.
I will run this statement, free of syntax
errors, and we get an error stating that every
column in a table must be unique.
Again, a runtime error is an error that is
not caused by a badly written query.
A runtime error occurs when a well-written
query attempts to do something to a database
that cannot be done.